Guide to the Walter Weir Papers, 1909-1996 and undated, bulk 1950-1990 RL.01362
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Walter Weir papers
1909-1996 and undated, bulk 1950-1990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Weir, Walter
RL.01362
14 Linear Feet
Walter Weir was an advertising executive, marketing and communications consultant, and professor of advertising. He worked for a number of agencies, including N.W. Ayer & Sons, J. M. Mathes, Lord & Thomas, and Kenyon & Eckhardt. He founded Walter Weir, Inc., which merged into larger firms over the years, was co-owner of Switzerland-based La Borie/Weir S.A., and headed Walter Weir Communications, Inc. Weir also taught advertising at the University of Tennessee and Temple University, wrote three books on advertising, annonymously authored the Creative Man's Corner column in Advertising Age magazine for 25 years, and composed numerous speeches, articles, short stories, poems, songs, and musicals. The Walter Weir Papers span the years 1909 through 1996, the bulk of which cover the 1950s through the early 1990s. The collection consists of audiocassettes, audiotapes, correspondence, course materials, clippings, musical scores, photographs, presentations, proofs, print advertising copy, radio advertisement scripts, songs, speeches, writings, and voiceovers documenting Weir's career in advertising, marketing, consulting, and teaching. The collection also documents Weir's prose, poems, and musicals, as well as his relationship with son Anthony Weir. Agencies and clients represented include the Alexander Proudfoot Company, Green Thumb Corporation, Interhydro AG, Jackson & Perkins Co., La Borie/Weir SA, Ralston Purina, Stratford of Texas, Inc., Walter Weir, Inc., and Walter Weir Communications, Inc. The collection also includes materials relating to Crain Communications Inc., which published Advertising Age, as well as the University of Tennessee and Temple University, and Weir's correspondence with Oscar Hammerstein II.
Approximately 7,700 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
Permission is not granted for publication of the contents of folder entitled N.W. Ayer Oral History Program interview with Walter Weir. The user is responsible for obtaining permission to publish from the interviewers.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Walter Weir Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2002.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1909 Mar. 27 Born Walter John Weir, Philadephia, PA
1928 N.W. Ayer advertising agency in Philadelphia
Circa 1930-circa 1938 Blackman Agency (later to become Compton Advertising)
1931 Apr. 18 Married Kathryn Ternan
1936 May 3 Anthony Weir (son) born
1938-1941 VP and creative director, J. M. Mathes, Inc.
1941-1942 VP and creative director, Lord & Thomas agency
1942-1945 VP and creative director, Kenyon & Eckhardt
1945-1951 President, Walter Weir, Inc.
1951 Executive VP, Donahue & Coe Merger with Donahue & Coe
1960 On the Writing of Advertising (McGraw Hill Series in Marketing and Advertising) published
1963 Truth in Advertising and Other Heresies (NY: McGraw Hill) published
1964 Wife Kathryn died. Merger with Ellington & Co. to create West, Weir & Bartel
1965 Mar. 29 Marries Johanna Rae
1968 Merger with MacManus, John & Adams
1970 Retires to Bequia, St. Vincent & the Grenadines (Caribbean Islands)
1978 Professor of Advertising, University of Tennessee College of Communications
1980 Professor of Advertising, Temple University School of Communications and Theater
1986 Communications advisor, Proudfoot Communications (Alexander Proudfoot Worldwide Family of Cos.)
1993 How to Create Interest-Evoking, Sales-Inducing, Non-Irritating Advertising (Haworth Press) published
1996 Mar. 2 Died.
Collection Overview
The Walter Weir Papers span the years 1909 through 1996, the bulk of which cover the 1950s through the early 1990s. The collection consists of audiocassettes, audiotapes, correspondence, course materials, clippings, musical scores, photographs, presentations, proofs, print advertising copy, radio advertisement scripts, songs, speeches, writings, and voiceovers documenting Weir's career in advertising, marketing, consulting, and teaching. The collection also documents Weir's prose, poems, and musicals, as well as his relationship with son Anthony Weir. Agencies and clients represented include the Alexander Proudfoot Company, Green Thumb Corporation, Interhydro AG, Jackson & Perkins Co., La Borie/Weir SA, Ralston Purina, Stratford of Texas, Inc., Walter Weir, Inc., and Walter Weir Communications, Inc. The collection also includes materials relating to Crain Communications Inc., which published Advertising Age, as well as the University of Tennessee and Temple University, and Weir's correspondence with Oscar Hammerstein II.
This collection is organized into six series: Musical, Personal, Professional, Teaching, Writings and Speeches, and Audiovisual Materials.
The Musical Series documents Weir's work on scores and scripts for musical theatre. Much of the correspondence in this series narrates Weir's efforts to produce a musical based on the Frederic Wakeman novel The Hucksters. Includes correspondence with Oscar Hammerstein II.
The Personal Series contains biographical data about Weir and his involvement with family and friends through correspondence, clippings, greeting cards, photographs, and handwritten notes. The bulk of the correspondence documents Weir's personal and professional relationship with his son, Anthony.
The Professional Series documents Weir's career in advertising, marketing, and communications. Advertising copy, clippings, correspondence, proposals, presentations, and legal and financial papers represent Weir's work from the beginning of his career at N.W. Ayer through the evolution of his company, Walter Weir, Inc., as well as through subsequent business ventures, including La Borie/Weir SA, Walter Weir Communications, Inc., and freelance consulting work.
The Teaching Series represents Weir's work, following his official retirement from the advertising industry, as a professor of advertising, marketing and communications at the University of Tennessee and Temple University. Correspondence, course materials, and clippings document this extension of Weir's career from his introduction to and retirement from the academy.
The Writings and Speeches Series includes fiction, poetry, and non-fiction written by Weir on subjects both related and unrelated to advertising. Among these are articles published in Printer's Ink and Advertising Age; unpublished manuscripts of autobiographies, bound copies of Weir's book How to Create Interest-Evoking, Sales-Inducing, Non-Irritating Advertising; transcripts of talks and addresses Weir gave about advertising throught his career, including an address for the James Webb Young Foundation; and correspondence with Rance Crain of Crain Communications, Inc., publisher of Advertising Age.
The Audiovisual Series includes auiotapes and audiocassettes of advertising-related talks and addresses, notably for the Million Dollar Round Table Tape Cassette Program. In addition, there are radio spots for clients including Mountain Dew, E.F. Hutton, and Merril, Lynch, Pierce, Fenner & Beane, as well as samples of voiceovers and radio commercial productions.
Large-format print materials have been removed from their original series locations and relocated to Oversize Materials. Relocated items have been indicated in the Detailed Description of the Collection by notes enclosed in brackets.
Related Material
Materials related to those contained in this collection may be found in other Hartman Center collections, including the Anthony Weir Papers, 1936-1996 and undated, the D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Archives, 1929-1989, the Bates Worldwide, Inc. Records, 1934-2003 and undated, the Jeffrey Collection of Diamond Promotional Materials, 1939-1988, bulk 1974-1988, the J. Walter Thompson Company. Wallace W. Elton Papers, 1919-1990, and the J. Walter Thompson Company. Colin Dawkins Papers, 1776-1986.
Scores; Scripts (documents); Speeches; Voice-overs; Audiocassettes; Advertising copy; Advertising agencies -- United States; Audiotapes; Photographs; College teachers -- United States; Marketing; Marketing -- Study and teaching (Higher); Marketing -- United States; Proofs (printed matter); Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising executives -- United States -- Biography; Clippings (information artifacts); Advertising -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Musicals; Radio advertising; Hammerstein, Oscar, 1895-1960 -- Correspondence; Green Thumb Inc.; Crain Communications Inc.; Advertising age; Ralston Purina Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Jackson & Perkins Co; Hammerstein, Oscar, 1895-1960; Weir, Walter; Weir, Anthony, 1936-; University of Tennessee, Knoxville -- Faculty; Temple University -- Faculty; Weir, Walter
- Musical Series, 1950-1995 and undated, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes scores, scripts and correspondence from Weir's work for musical theatre, the bulk of which is related to The Hucksters, a musical comedy he composed based on Frederic Wakeman's eponymous book. Large format items have been removed to Oversize Materials and the relocation indicated in brackets. Arranged alphabetically.
  - The Hucksters
    Includes drafts of playscripts and musical scores, along with correspondence representing Weir's efforts to get the musical produced. Some items have been removed to Oversize Materials. Arranged Alphabetically.
    - Copyright certificate, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Musical Score, undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
      Separated Materials note
      [Some items removed to Oversize Materials Box 20.]
    - Playscript, undated (Box 1)
  - The Poison Maid
    Consists of drafts of an original musical, which Weir composed and tried to get produced. Includes correspondence between Weir and Oscar Hammerstein II. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Notes and workshop material, circa 1950 (Box 1)
    - Playscript and correspondence with Oscar Hammerstein II, 1950 (Box 1)
    - Synopsis, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Other Music
    Includes Weir's work on various other musical compositions. Several items have been removed to Oversize Materials. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Copyright certificates for songs entitled Take-Off Kiss, Little Cowboy Boots, Love Me Now, and White Man, 1955 and circa 1970 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence regarding copyright of song entitled The Merril, Lynch, Pierce, Fenner & Beane, 1952 (Box 1)
    - Songs
      - Australia Trip, 1962 (Box 1)
        [Removed to Oversize Materials, Box 20.]
      - Little Cowboy Boots, 1955 (Box 1)
      - Madison Avenue, undated (Box 1)
      - Puerto Rico, USA, undated (Box 1)
      - Somewhere out in the morning, 1995 and undated (Box 1)
      - Speaking Spanish, undated (Box 1)
      - The Bulletin Song, undated (Box 1)
      - White Man, undated (Box 1)
- Personal Series, 1935-1996 and undated, 1 box
  Includes correspondence, clippings, greeting cards, photographs, and handwritten notes pertaining to Weir's personal life. All correspondence between Weir and his son, Anthony (Tony) Weir is filed separately from general personal correspondence. Some notes from Tony's children are filed with correspondence between Walter and Anthony. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Clippings, 1942-1978 and undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1996, 3 folders (Box 1)
    Contains personal correspondence unrelated to Weir's professional, musical, or teaching work. All correspondence between Weir and his son, Anthony (Tony), can be found in the folder entitled Correspondence with Anthony Weir.
  - Correspondence with Anthony Weir, 1955-1996 and undated, 7 folders (Box 2)
    General note
    Contains all correspondence between Weir and his son, Anthony (Tony). Includes some letters from and to Anthony's children, Tim and Matt.
  - Family occasions (Christmas cards, birth and death announcements, weddings, reunion), 1935-1981 (Box 2)
  - Handwritten notes, 1975 and undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1974, 1985 and undated (Box 2)
  - Promises Fulfilled: One view of the life of Walter Weir, 27 March 1909-9 March 1996, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Resume, 1985 (Box 2)
- Professional Series, 1909-1995 and undated, bulk 1970-1989, 9 boxes
  Includes advertising copy; correspondence; clippings; legal and financial documents; and business proposals that represent Weir's agency and freelance work in advertising, marketing, and communications. The bulk of the material represents work generated by Walter Weir Communications, especially work for Proudfoot Communications Inc., and Weir's partnership in La Borie/Weir, SA.. Arranged alphabetically by agency.
  - La Borie/Weir, S.A., 1970-1986 and undated
    Includes all correspondence, proposals, and other printed material generated with respect to Weir's business venture with Walter La Borie. The bulk of the material pertains to the company's investment in Interhydro AG's Luwasa hydroculture technology. Some materials in French.
    - A concept for obtaining a sizable share of the deoderant market at minimal cost, undated (Box 3)
    - A marketing plan for improving the sale of Life Savers, circa 1975 (Box 3)
    - A new concept in Resort Operation for consideration by Sheraton International, circa 1975 (Box 3)
    - A plan for the successful promotion of sales of existing and designated projects under an organization to be known as the National Condominium Association, undated (Box 3)
    - A proposal for the Dole Corporation, undated (Box 3)
    - A unique, timely, highly profitable opportunity in men's suits..., circa 1975 (Box 3)
    - Chinese fast food proposals, 1974 and undated (Box 3)
    - Cigarette brand marketing, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Concept for an OTC item with a self-prescribing brand name that has no presently available counterpart, undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence from Weir to La Borie concerning continuance of La Borie/Weir SA in the event of either of their deaths, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence regarding Debrett's Peerage Ltd., 1978 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence regarding ownership and revenue following the death of Walter La Borie, 1981-1987 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with accountant Suzanne Hefti, 1971-1981 (Box 3)
    - Cosmetics and perfume, circa 1975 (Box 3)
    - Escrow agreement between Green Thumb Corp. and Interhydro AG, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Floral mass marketing proposals, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Golden Sands, 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Green Thumb Corp. correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Green Thumb Corp. royalties reports, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
    - Hughes, Hubbard & Reed, 1971-1976 (Box 3)
    - Interhydro AG correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
      [Some items removed to Oversize Materials, Box 21.]
    - Interhydro AG vs. Casa Flora, Inc., 1978 (Box 3)
    - Interhydro AG vs. Ralston Purina, et. al., 1977 (Box 3)
    - Jackson & Perkins correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 4)
    - Jackson & Perkins royalties reports, 1979-1982 (Box 4)
    - Legal agreement between Interhydro AG and Green Thumb Corporation, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Legal agreement between Interhydro AG and Jackson & Perkins (J&P), 1979 (Box 4)
    - Legal agreement between Interhydro AG and Ralston Purina Company, 1977 (Box 4)
      [Removed to Oversize Materials, Box 21.]
    - Legal agreement with Interhydro AG, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Luwasa System, 1973-1985, 2 folders (Box 4)
      [Some items Removed to Oversize Materials, Box 21.]
    - Statuts de La Borie/Weir SA, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Stratford of Texas and Green Thumb Corp. bankruptcy, 1976-1978 (Box 4)
    - Stratford of Texas and Green Thumb Corp. restraining order and injunction, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Stratford Overseas, Inc. correspondence, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Sworn deposition for Interhydro AG by Walter Weir, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Tempop, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Truman Fossum, 1960, 1975, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Volkswagon proposal, circa 1979 (Box 4)
  - Walter Weir, Inc., 1949-1985
    Includes documents pertaining to all companies derived from Walter Weir, Inc. through merger or acquisition (See Biographical Note). Arranged alphabetically.
    - Correspondence from Publicker Industries, Inc. regarding ad copy, 1949 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence regarding D'Arcy-MacManus & Masius tax court case, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence regarding income from MacManus, John & Adams, Inc. (later, D'Arcy-MacManus & Masius), 1970-1976 (Box 4)
    - Donahue & Coe, Inc. CORE, Inc. proposal, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Harvard Business Review advertisements, 1949-1950 and 1985 (Box 4)
    - Plan and Agreement for Merger between A. West, Weir & Bartel Inc. and MacManus, John & Adams Inc. 1968 (Box 4)
  - Walter Weir Communications, Inc., 1976-1994
    Consists of correspondence, advertising campaigns, and marketing proposals generated by the communications agency that Weir ran toward the end of his career. The bulk of the papers represent Weir's work for the Alexander Proudfoot Company and The Pleasantville Plan, Ltd., a mail-order retailing business directed by John C. Holme. Among The Pleasantville Plan materials are papers relating to a campaign designed to market Berlitz language study products. Arranged alphabetically
    - Advertising and Product Concepts for Market Expansion of Slimfast, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Alexander Proudfoot Company, L.P., 1986-1988, 1-12 of 32 folders (Box 5)
    - Alexander Proudfoot Company, L.P. (continued), 1986-1988, 13-21 of 32 folders (Box 6)
    - Alexander Proudfoot Company, L.P. (continued), 1986-1988, 22-32 of 32 folders (Box 7)
    - Appraisal of State of Illinois Tourism Program Research and Planning and Campaign Effectiveness, circa 1988 (Box 8)
    - A Plan for marketing Charles L. Rolison and Sons in the area of top price real estate, 1977-1979 (Box 8)
    - A Plan to Encourage More Purchasers of Real Estate to Insist on Surveys Made by Land Surveyors, undated (Box 8)
    - A Unique Marketing Concept and Opportunity for Calvin Klein Hip Briefs, circa 1988 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence from Principal Mutual, 1991 (Box 8)
    - House of Seagram, 1990 (Box 8)
    - How to increase brand awareness of Wella shampoo and conditioner, circa 1980 (Box 8)
    - Keep America Out Front, 1983-1984 (Box 8)
    - L'Eggs, 1975-1980 (Box 8)
    - Mano Swartz furs, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Marketing plan for Envirogenics, Inc., circa 1990 (Box 8)
    - Marsh & McLennan Companies, 1991 (Box 8)
    - Million Dollar Round Table, 1980, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Newspaper marketing for advertising and circulation, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Novelty toilet seat and liquor packaging ideas, 1990-1994 (Box 8)
    - Oil of Olay idea for Avon, 1984 (Box 8)
    - One Hundred Pipers idea for Seagrams, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Proposal for a Leadership Move by Hiram Walker in the Distilling Industry, circa 1990 (Box 8)
    - SCMP Weekly (South China Morning Post), 1993 (Box 8)
    - Scott Paper Company, circa 1990 (Box 8)
    - Teacher's Highland Cream, circa 1990 (Box 8)
    - The Double Jeopardy of Sales Promotions, by John Philip Jones, 1993 (Box 8)
    - The Pleasantville Plan (John C. Holme), 1977-1990, 8 folders (Box 9)
    - The Tseng Image, circa 1990 (Box 9)
    - Three Questions and a Number of Responses for Consideration and Testing, submitted to Seagrams, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Tool Crib, 1994 (Box 9)
    - University of Florida report, 1993 (Box 9)
  - Other Materials, 1909-1996
    Includes miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, and other assorted printed material related to Weir's professional career in advertising and peripheral business ventures. Among these, there are unsolicited proposals and cold-call letters, a transcript of Weir's interview for the N.W. Ayer Oral History Program, a secrecy agreement for intellectual property, and STARCH readership materials. Arranged alphabetically.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restriction on Access: Permission is not granted for publication of the contents of folder entitled N.W. Ayer Oral History Program interview with Walter Weir. The user is responsible for obtaining permission to publish from the interviewers.
    - Awards and nominations, 1990-1995 (Box 10)
    - Campbell's Travel, 1973-1978 (Box 10)
    - Clippings and printed material, 1983-1993 and undated, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1979, 5 folders (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1989, 1-3 of 7 folders (Box 10)
    - Correspondence (continued), 1980-1989, 4-7 of 7 folders (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1996, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Freelance ideas, 1976-1993 (Box 11)
    - N.W. Ayer & Sons, images of Mariner and Merchant Building, 1946 (Box 11)
    - N.W. Ayer Oral History Program interview with Walter Weir, 1989 (Box 11)
    - Obituary of Marcus Aurelius Goodrich, 1991 (Box 11)
    - Photocopy of excerpt from Advertising Development, by Edgar W. Coleman, copyright 1909 (Box 11)
    - Real estate salesman registration card, 1980 (Box 11)
    - Secrecy Agreement for information in the field of air conditioning, 1995 (Box 11)
    - Starch Readership Report, 1986 (Box 11)
    - Starch Tested Copy, circa 1960 (Box 11)
- Teaching Series, 1958-1995, bulk 1975-1995, 1 box
  Includes all materials relating to Weir's teaching career, the bulk of which represents his time at the University of Tennessee and Temple University. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Temple University, 1980-1986
    - Campaigns class, 1986, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1986, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Retirement, 1986 (Box 12)
    - So-Called Industrial Advertising, circa 1980 (Box 12)
  - University of Tennessee, 1976-1980
    - Advertising 3000, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
    - Contract for Personal Services between The University of Tennessee and Walter J. Weir, 1979 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1980, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Course Preparation, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
    - Review of Hafer and White manuscript, 1980 (Box 12)
    - Students' teacher evaluations, 1979 (Box 12)
  - Other Materials, 1958-1995, bulk 1975-1995
    Includes other materials related to Weir's teaching career that is not directly related to his work for the University of Tennessee or Temple University. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Bell Telephone v. Yellow Pages case, 1985 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence regarding teaching opportunity at Northwestern University, 1980 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence regarding teaching opportunity at University of North Carolina, 1985 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence with University of Texas, 1988 (Box 12)
    - Job-seeking correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 12)
    - Letter of recommendation for former student, 1987 (Box 12)
    - Publication of text written at Temple, 1991 (Box 12)
    - Reaction to Why Ad Pros Can't Teach, by David Herzbrun, 1992-1993 (Box 12)
    - Student correspondence, 1986, 1988 (Box 12)
    - Subliminal Advertising, correspondence regarding Wilson Bryan Key and Jack Haberstroh books, 1958, 1982, and 1992-1995 (Box 12)
- Writings and Speeches Series, circa 1928-1994 and undated, 7 boxes